A Guide to the Papers of the Virginia Military Institute Superintendent. Francis H. Smith, 1839-1889
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Papers of the Virginia Military Institute Superintendent. Francis H. Smith 1839-1889
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
RG02.01.01
ca. 30 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Biographical Information
Francis H. Smith served for fifty years (1839-1889) as VMI's first Superintendent. Smith was born in 1812, graduated from West Point in 1833, and came to Lexington, Virginia in 1839 to lead the newly established Virginia Military Institute. He died in March 1890, a few months after his retirement as Superintendent. He was known as the builder and --after the Civil War-- rebuilder of VMI. His official correspondence spans the period 1839-1889, with few gaps. The Civil War era and earlier letters survived Gen. David Hunter's destruction of many Institute buildings in June 1864. Smith corresponded with the notable military, educational, and political leaders of his time, making the correspondence a rich resource for scholars.
Scope and Content
These files constitute the major record series generated by the office of Francis H. Smith, VMI’s first Superintendent. He served from 1839-1889. The records, (ca. 30 linear feet) consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence, order books, speeches and publications, personal file, and subject files.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in 6 series:
Records Series
Incoming Correspondence, 1839-1870; 1885-1889
Outgoing Correspondence, 1839-1889
Order Books, 1839-1889
Speeches, Addresses, Publications
Subject Files
Personal File, Papers, and related
Index Terms
Smith, Francis H. -- (Francis Henney), -- 1812-1890.; Military schools -- Southern States.; Virginia Military Institute -- History -- 19th century.; Military education -- Virginia -- History -- 19th century.; Virginia Military Institute -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contents List
- Incoming Correspondence 1839-1870; 1885-1889
  The incoming letters dated 1839-1870 are arranged according to a numbering system used by Smith's office. Within each year, each incoming letter was assigned a letter number and filed in numerical order; some years were broken down into alphabetical sections with a separate numerical sequence for each section. The later letters, 1885-1889, are arranged alphabetically within each year. There is no separate sequence for 1860, although a small number of 1860 letters appear in the 1861 file. No incoming letter file exists for the period 1870-1884.
  - Letters, Numbered 1839-1844 (Box 1)
  - Letters, Numbered 1845-1846 (Box 2)
  - Letters, Numbered 1847-1848 (Box 3)
  - Letters, Numbered 1849-1850 (Box 4)
  - Letters, Numbered 1851 (Box 5)
  - Letters, Numbered 1852 (Box 6)
  - Letters, Numbered 1853 (Box 7)
  - Letters, Numbered 1854 (Box 8)
  - Letters, Numbered 1855 1855 (Box 9)
  - Letters, Numbered, 1-599 1856 (Box 10)
  - 1856, Letters 600-863 (Box 11)
  - Letters, Numbered 1857 (Box 12)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-L 1858 (Box 13)
  - Letters, Numbered, M-Y 1858 (Box 14)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-K 1859 (Box 15)
  - Letters, Numbered, L-Z 1859 (Box 16)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-D 1861 (Box 17)
  - Letters, Numbered, E-L 1861 (Box 18)
  - Letters, Numbered, M-R 1861 (Box 19)
  - Letters, Numbered, S-Z 1861 (Box 20)
  - Letters, Numbered, S-Z 1862 1862 (Box 21)
  - Letters, Numbered, H-P 1862 (Box 22)
  - Letters,Numbered, Q-Z 1862 (Box 23)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-E 1863 (Box 24)
  - Letters, Numbered, F-L 1863 (Box 25)
  - Letters, Numbered, M-R 1863 (Box 26)
  - Letters, Numbered, R-Z 1863 (Box 27)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-J 1864 (Box 28)
  - Letters, Numbered, K-R 1864 (Box 29)
  - Letters, Numbered, S-Z 1864 (Box 30)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-Z 1865 (Box 31)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-G 1866 (Box 32)
  - Letters, Numbered, H-Q 1866 (Box 33)
  - Letters, Numbered, R-Z 1866 (Box 34)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-F 1867 (Box 35)
  - Letters, Numbered, G-M 1867 (Box 36)
  - Letters, Numbered, N-T 1867 (Box 37)
  - Letters, Numbered, U-Z 1867 (Box 38)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-D 1868 (Box 39)
  - Letters, Numbered, E-L 1868 (Box 40)
  - Letters, Numbered, M-R 1868 (Box 41)
  - Letters, Numbered, S-Z 1868 (Box 42)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-Z 1869 (Box 43)
  - Letters, Numbered, A-D 1870 (Box 44)
  - Letters, Numbered, E-K 1870 (Box 45)
  - Letters, Numbered, C-Y 1870 (Box 46)
  - Letters, Numbered, L-P 1870 (Box 47)
  - Letters, Numbered, R-Z 1870 (Box 48)
  - 1885, A-Z 1885 (Box 49)
  - 1886, A-Z 1886 (Box 50)
  - 1887, A-N 1887 (Box 51)
  - 1887, O-Z 1887 (Box 52)
  - 1888, A-O 1888 (Box 53)
  - 1888, P-Z 1888 (Box 54)
  - 1889, A-O 1889 (Box 55)
  - 1889, P-Z 1889 (Box 56)
- Outgoing Correspondence 1839-1889, Bound volumes in boxes. Letterpress copybooks from 1860-1889, 79 volumes; vols. from 1860-1869 contain some sections that are very difficult to decipher. Internal indexes in each volume beginning 1849.
  - Letterbook 1840 JUL 25-1844 FEB 8 (Volume 1)
  - Letterbook 1840 FEB 10-1848 DEC 30 (Volume 2)
  - Letterbook 1849 JAN 1-1851 AUG 9 (Volume 3)
  - Letterbook 1851 AUG 11-1854 NOV 22 (Volume 4)
  - Letterbook 1854 NOV 29-1857 JUN 11 (Volume 5)
  - Letterbook 1857 JUN 11-1859 DEC 30 (Volume 6)
  - Letterbook 1860 JAN 2-1860 JUN 7 (Volume 7)
  - Letterbook 1860 JUN 7-1860 OCT 1 (Volume 8)
  - Letterbook 1860 OCT 1-1861 FEB 13 (Volume 9)
  - Letterbook 1861 FEB 13-1861 SEP 24 (Volume 10)
  - Letterbook 1861 SEP 25-1862 AUG 27 (Volume 11)
  - Letterbook 1862 AUG 28-1863 JUL 17 (Volume 12)
  - Letterbook 1863 JUL 17-1863 DEC 31 (Volume 13)
  - Letterbook 1864 JAN 1-1864 AUG 8 (Volume 14)
  - Gap - no extant records 1864 AUG 9- 1865 OCT 30 (Volume 0)
  - Letterbook 1865 OCT 31-1866 AUG 15 (Volume 15)
  - Letterbooks, multiple volumes 1866 AUG 15-1889 DEC 31 (Volume 16-79)
- Order Books 1839-1889, bound volumes
  Order Books, containing General and Special Orders, document all aspects of Institute life during the Smith Administration. They contain information about everyday cadet life, academics, training, and individual cadets. Some boxes contain multiple volumes; the box label date is inclusive for all volumes within a box.
  - Order Book 1839 NOV 11-1852 JAN 14 (Volume 1)
  - Order Book, Summer Camp 1842-1846 (Volume 2)
  - Order Book 1852 JAN 5-1857 JUL 17 (Volume 3)
  - Order Book 1857 JUL 31-1860 DEC 31 (Volume 4)
  - Order Book 1861 JAN 1-1863 AUG 31 (Volume 5)
  - Order Book 1862 JAN 17-1864 MAY 7 (Volume 6)
    This volume was carried away by a Union soldier, Private J. O. Humphreys of the 1st Ohio Artillery, after Hunter's Raid in June 1864. He used the empty pages in the back of the volume to record this account of his unit's activities from late April through early July, 1864. The diary has been transcribed and is also available on the VMI Archives website.
  - 1863 SEP 1-1865 MAR 31 (Volume 7)
    This volume also contains a portion of a demerit book for 1866-1867, and a fragment of a matriculation book. The latter includes a copy of entries from 1839-August 1856, and original signatures from August 1856 through June 1861.
  - No Order Book for this period 1865 APR-NOV (Volume 0)
  - Order Book 1865 DEC 9-1867 JUL 25 (Volume 8)
  - Order Book, multiple volumes 1867 SEP 3-1889 DEC 31 (Volume 9-22)
- Speeches, Addresses, Publications 1841-1879 (Box 1)
  - Lecture on the History of Mathematics 1841 (Folder 1)
  - Elimination between two unknonw equations with two unknown quantities... 1842 (Folder 2)
  - Regulations of Military Institutions applied to the Conduct of COmmon Schools. 1849 (Folder 3)
  - College Reform 1851 (Folder 4)
  - Memoir of Dr. Thomas Henderson of the Unistited State Army by his son-in-law 1854 (Folder 5)
  - Introductory Address to the Crops of Cadets of the V irgnia Military Institute on the Resumption of Academic Duties, September 2, 1856. 1856 (Folder 6)
  - Scientific Education in Europe 1859 (Folder 7)
  - Discourse on the Life and Character of Lt. Gen. Thoms. J. Jackson 1863 (Folder 8)
  - Introductory Lecture Read Bdefore the Corps of Cadets on the Resumption of Academic Duties of the Virginia Military Institute at the Alms House, Richmond, Va., December 28, 1864 1864 (Folder 9)
  - The Inner Life of the VMI Cadet. Its Responsibilities and its Privileges. An Introductory address to the Corps of Cadets of the Virgnia Military Institute on the Resumption of the Academic Exercises, September 10, 1866. 1866 (Folder 10)
  - Gymnastic and Technical Education in the Virginia Military Institute 1871 (Folder 11)
  - Synopsis of Argument of Gen. Smith in Behalf of the Claims of the Virginia Military Institute 1871 (Folder 12)
  - The Schools and Schoomasters of Virginia in the Olden Time. An Addresss 1874 (Folder 13)
  - Synopsis of Argument of Gen. F. H. Smith...before the Joint Committee of the Senate and House of Delegates of Virginia, January 25, 1876 1876 (Folder 14)
  - Annual Report of the Board of Managers of the Male Orphan Society of Richmond, with an Address by Prof. Francis H. Smith 1876 (Folder 15)
  - West Point Fifty Years Ago. An Address delivered before the Association of Graduates of the U. S. Military Academy at the Annual Reunion, June 12, 1879 1879 (Folder 16)
- Subject Files 1839-1889
  - Cadet Letters of Application and Recommendation 1839-1864 (gaps), 5 boxes
    In the 19th century, students applying for admission to VMI submitted letters from parents and others in support of the application. This subject file consists of these letters, and includes both matriculating and non-matriculating students. Students who ultimately enrolled at VMI will have a more complete file in the alumni biographical files collection. However, students who did not enroll may have no other information on file.
    Alphabetical
  - Faculty Applications, incomplete, 19th century. 1839-1860; 1884, Folders in 1 box
    Faculty applications, historical. Letters of application and supporting letters of recommendation submitted for several faculty & staff positions. Includes positions of Professor of Modern Languages, Physical Sciences, Steward, Quartermaster. This file only relates to a few specific positions.
  - Washington College (now Washington & Lee University). 1845-1860, Folders in 1 box
    Several items, 1845, concerning a complaint lodged by Washington College against VMI, which ultimately led to a severance of academic ties between the two institutions. Prof. George Dodd Armstrong represented the College on this issue. For a full account, see 100 Years at VMI (William Couper), vol. 1, pps. 139-147. One unrelated document from 1860.
  - George Washington Statue 1856-1866, Folders in 1 box
    Includes letter from Francis H. Smith to Dr. Galt inviting him to the statue dedication; original manuscript of remarks made at the Washington Statue dedication on July 3, 1856 by William B. Taliaferro, Revd. John H. Bowcock, Francis H. Smith. Information (photocopies, 1864-1866) concerning the confiscation of the statue by Gen. Hunter's troops and its return from West Virginia in 1866, including copies of letters from David H. Strother of Gen. Hunter's staff.
  - Academic Departments Annual Reports to Superintendent Smith 1843-1848;1865-1889, Folders in 1 box
    Examples of academic department annual reports from the 19th century. These reports from the various academic departments were submitted to the Superintendent and help to document the early academic history of the Institute. This file includes early reports by John T. L. Preston (Languages), and Thomas H. Williamson (Engineering), as well as reports by other early faculty members. The series has many gaps; for example, none from the 1850's. The reports reflect some subjects that are no longer taught, e.g., Latin, drawing, mineralogy.
  - Financial Claims Against Cadets 1871-1873, Folders in 1 box
    19th century legal documents. Records of VMI attorneys Letcher, Maury and Letcher relating to collection of cadet debts after Civil War, 1871-1873
  - Frederick Volck Document 1870, 1 item
    Three page memorandum of agreement (July 13, 1870) between sculptor Frederick Volck and VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith. Volck was to complete a bronze equestrian statue of Gen. Thomas J. Jackson, but the project was never finished. (See the book "One Hundred Years at VMI" by William Couper, vol 3, p. 212, for an account of Volck's relationship with VMI).
  - Court Martial and Board of Inquiry Records 1848-1854; 1881-1898, Bound volume; documents in box/folders
    19th century historical court martial and board of inquiry records. Includes bound volume, 1848-1854, containing early VMI Courts Martial proceedings, including trial of Cadet James Walker for disrespectful behavior toward Major Thomas Jackson (Stonewall), May 1852. One box, misc. cases, 1881-1898. Records of other cases are located in the Order Books.
- Biographical Material, Personal Papers, and Related Research Notes. 1858-ongoing
  Miscellaneous personal papers, biographical and genealogical information; and research notes compiled by historians
  - Biographical File 1890-ongoing
    Biographical, genealogical, printed material and other related information compiled over decades. This material is used as a reference file.
  - Personal Papers, Miscellaneous 1858-1890
    These miscellaneous Francis H. Smith and Smith family personal papers were once held by a Smith descendant and subsequently donated to VMI. Much of the material is in poor condition. The most significant items are 2 volumes of personal letters written while on his trip to Europe in 1858, along with a scrapbook containing engravings of places visited. The material also contains misc. personal correspondence, including one letter from Scott Shipp thanking Smith for his condolences upon the death of Shipp's wife. Two items were transferred to the VMI Museum:a pair of Smith's eyeglasses; anda small oil portrait of Sarah (Sara) Henderson Smith, his wife.
  - "Old Spex of the VMI", unpublished biography ca. 1940
    Unpublished typescript by Francis H. Smith III. This is the only full length biography of Francis H. Smith and is a useful source for information not found elsewhere.
  - Edwin L. Dooley Research Notes 1990-2013
    Edwin L. Dooley, Jr., former Executive Assistant to the Superintendent and Secretary to the Board of Visitors, is also a historian who has studied Francis H. Smith in depth. This material comprises his research material relating to Smith's personal and professional life.